<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rdf:RDF
   xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
   xmlns:owl="http://www.w3.org/2002/07/owl#"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#"
>
  <rdf:Description rdf:about="https://w3id.org/ido">
    <dc:creator>Silvio Peroni (http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0530-4305)</dc:creator>
    <owl:versionIRI rdf:resource="https://w3id.org/ido/0.5.1"/>
    <dc:description xml:lang="en">The Imperial Data Ontology (IDO) is an OWL 2 DL ontology that allows the description of selling data of fashion design industries.

The development of IDO is one of the outcomes of the agreement between the [University of Bologna](http://www.unibo.it/en) and [Imperial](http://www.imperialfashion.com/en/). Part of this agreement is dedicated to the use of Semantic Web technologies for the description and analysis of selling data of Imperial, and, more generally, of fashion design industries.

Currently, IDO allows one to describe the following scenarios in OWL.


### Scenario 1

The company online selling system allows people subscribed to the Imperial online platform to order a stock keeping unit available in the online catalogue in order to receive it at a specified address (currently characterised by a province and its related region). Each ordered stock keeping unit is identified (in some way) by (1) a unique code, (2) the genre (male or female) for whom the item was created, (3) its size, and (4) its colour. Each user of the Imperial online platform has assigned a genre (male or female), a born date, and the province and region of her home.


### Scenario 2

The catalogue of the company includes a detailed description of all the styles (identified by a code) available for selling and/or sold in the past to a certain client. Each style is then associated to a particular category, such as "sweater", "trousers", "jacket", etc. These categories are fixed at a certain time but can be modified (adding more ones or reorganising their hierarchical structure) in the future.


### Scenario 3

A style defines the design of an article of a certain category (e.g., shirt, dress, trousers) and it was designed for one or more genre ("male", "female", or both). An item is a particular realisation of a style according to a certain textile, and proposed for a particular season.

Each item can be made available in different sizes and colours. Any combination of these characteristics defines a stock keeping unit. The piece that is effectively produced, finally, is an exemplar of a stock keeping unit.


### Scenario 4

On the 15th of December 2015, a particular stock keeping unit of a certain item, proposed for the season Autumn-Winter 2015, has COGS set to 15 euros, sell-in set to 24 euros, and sell-out set to 39 euros - all prices are net and include VAT. By the end of the year, 5 pieces of this stock keeping unit were sold: two of them were acquired by a customer (with sell-out price), and three of them were sold to a retailer (with sell-in price). After the sales, which began on the 7th of January 2016, the sell-out price was discounted for the 10% of the amount (35,10 euros). Seven pieces of the same stock keeping unit were then bought by another customer (with discounted sell-out price). On the 15th of January, so as to satisfies the selling requirements during the sales, several pieces of the same stock keeping unit have been produced with a lower cogs (12 euros). 20 of those pieces were sold to a reseller with a lower sell-in price (19,20 euros).


### Scenario 5

On the 15th of January 2016, an order was prepared on the B2B distribution platform (sales channel: e-commerce), which includes 4 pieces (35 euros each) of a stock keeping unit, and other 3 pieces (57 euros each) of another stock keeping unit, for a total value of 311 euros. The invoice associated to that order has been created two days after (same distribution platform and sales channel); it describes the delivery of three pieces of the first stock keeping unit, and of 3 other pieces of the second stock keeping unit (same prices as described in the order). The missing piece of the first stock keeping unit has been substituted with another piece of the same item but with different colour, and has been sold at 37 euros. The total value of the invoice is 313 euros.</dc:description>
    <dc:rights xml:lang="en">This work is distributed under a [Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)](http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</dc:rights>
    <dc:title xml:lang="it">Ontologia per i dati di Imperial (IDO)</dc:title>
    <owl:imports rdf:resource="https://w3id.org/ido/items/1.0.1"/>
    <rdfs:comment xml:lang="it">L'Ontologia per i dati di Imperial (o Imperial Data Ontology, IDO) è un'ontologia OWL 2 DL creata per la descrizione dei dati di vendita di aziende di moda.</rdfs:comment>
    <owl:imports rdf:resource="https://w3id.org/ido/prices/1.0.1"/>
    <rdf:type rdf:resource="http://www.w3.org/2002/07/owl#Ontology"/>
    <dc:description xml:lang="it">L'Ontologia per i dati di Imperial (o Imperial Data Ontology, IDO) è un'ontologia OWL 2 DL creata per la descrizione dei dati di vendita di aziende di moda.

La creazione di IDO è uno degli output attesi dall'accordo siglato tra l'[Università di Bologna](http://www.unibo.it) e [Imperial](http://www.imperialfashion.com), che in parte prevede l'utilizzo di tecnologie proprie al Semantic Web per la descrizione e l'analisi dei dati relativi alle vendite dei capi di Imperial e, più genericamente, delle industrie di moda.

Allo stato attuale, IDO permette di descrivere in OWL i seguenti scenari applicativi.


### Scenario 1

Il sistema di vendite online messo a disposizione dall'azienda permette a delle persone iscritte alla piattaforma Imperial di ordinare un articolo gestito in magazzino messo a disposizione nel catalogo online e di riceverlo direttamente all'indirizzo specificato (caratterizzato da provincia e regione). Ogni articolo gestito in magazzino ordinato è identificato da un codice univoco, dal genere di destinazione (uomo o donna), dalla taglia e dal colore relativo. Ad ogni utente sono associati genere, data di nascita, provincia e regione di residenza.


### Scenario 2

L'anagrafe dell'azienda include una descrizione dettagliata di tutti i modelli (identificati da un codice) attualmente in vendita e/o venduti in passato ad un certo cliente. Ogni modello è associato ad una specifica categoria, come ad esempio "maglia", "pantalone", "giubbotto", ecc. Queste categorie sono fissate in un certo momento temporale, ma possono subire variazioni (sia di numero, sia di organizzazione gerarchica) in futuro.


### Scenario 3

Un modello è un particolare disegno di un articolo di una certa categoria (es., maglia, gonna, pantalone) e destinato ad uno o più generi di persone ("uomo", "donna" o entrambi). Un capo è una particolare realizzazione di un modello relativamente ad un certo tessuto, e viene proposto per una certa stagione.

Ogni capo può essere messo a disposizione in differenti taglie e colori. Una qualunque combinazione di queste caratteristiche definisce, in gergo, un articolo gestito in magazzino. Il pezzo effettivamente prodotto, invece, è un esemplare di un articolo gestito in magazzino.


### Scenario 4

In data 15 dicembre 2015, una particolare articolo gestito in magazzino di un certo capo per la stagione autunno-inverno 2015 ha un prezzo di cogs fissato a 15 euro, con sell-in di 24 euro e sell-out di 39 euro - tutti prezzi netti IVA. Prima della fine dell'anno sono stati venduti 5 pezzi di questo articolo gestito in magazzino, due a un consumatore finale (con prezzo di sell-out) e tre a un rivenditore (con prezzo di sell-in). A seguito dei saldi, iniziati il 7 gennaio 2016, il prezzo di sell-out è stato scontato del 10% (35,10 euro). Sette pezzi dello stesso articolo in magazzino sono stati comprati in questo periodo da un altro consumatore finale (con prezzo di sell-out scontato). Il 15 gennaio, per soddisfare il fabbisogno di vendita nel periodo dei saldi, sono stati messi in produzione diversi pezzi dello stesso articolo gestito in magazzino, ma con un prezzo di cogs inferiore fissato a 12 euro. Venti di questi pezzi sono stati veduti ad un rivenditore ad un prezzo di sell-in di 19,20 euro.


### Scenario 5

In data 15 gennaio 2016, viene effettuato un ordine (sulla piattaforma di distribuzione B2B e-commerce) che include un articolo gestito in magazzino per 4 quantità (35 euro a pezzo), e un altro articolo gestito in magazzino per un totale di 3 quantità (57 euro a pezzo), per un valore totale di 311 euro. La fattura emessa due giorni dopo (e associata all'ordine e utilizzando la medesima piattaforma di distribuzione) indica la spedizione di 3 pezzi del primo articolo gestito in magazzino, e di 3 pezzi del secondo articolo gestito in magazzino, allo stesso prezzo indicato sull'ordine. Il pezzo mancante relativo al primo articolo gestito in magazzino è stato sostituito con un altro pezzo dello stesso capo ma di colore diverso, venduto al prezzo di 37 euro. Il valore totale della fattura è di 313 euro.</dc:description>
    <rdfs:comment xml:lang="en">The Imperial Data Ontology (IDO) is an OWL 2 DL ontology that allows the description of selling data of fashion design industries.</rdfs:comment>
    <dc:description rdf:resource="https://w3id.org/ido/ido.png"/>
    <dc:date>2017-03-23</dc:date>
    <owl:versionInfo>0.5.1</owl:versionInfo>
    <dc:title xml:lang="en">Imperial Data Ontology (IDO)</dc:title>
    <owl:imports rdf:resource="https://w3id.org/ido/users/1.0.1"/>
    <owl:imports rdf:resource="https://w3id.org/ido/orders/1.0.1"/>
    <dc:rights xml:lang="it">Questo lavoro è distribuito sotto una licenza [Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)](http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</dc:rights>
    <rdfs:label>IDO</rdfs:label>
  </rdf:Description>
  <rdf:Description rdf:about="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#isDefinedBy">
    <rdf:type rdf:resource="http://www.w3.org/2002/07/owl#AnnotationProperty"/>
  </rdf:Description>
</rdf:RDF>
